One of my colleagues at input output
bought some ADA for his nephews and nieces.
And of course, I don't know any details about that.
But just imagine you want to
make a gift of ADA to a child.
So, you want the child to own the ADA, but
you only want the child to have access to the
ADA when he or she turns 18 or 21 or whatever.
And using Plutus, this is very easy to implement
a scheme like that, a vesting scheme like that.
So I copied the is data contract.
And into a new module that I called vesting.
And as our first example of a validator
that actually uses the context, I want
to try to implement this vesting idea.
So you put money into a script and only the
dedicated person can retrieve it, but only
once a certain deadline has been reached.
So the first step is to think about
the types of datum and redeemer.
And it makes sense to have the datum contain
exactly those two pieces of information,
the beneficiary and the deadline.
So let's do what we did at the end of last lecture.
Use a custom type for the datum,
I called it vesting datum.
It's a simple record type with these
two fields, beneficiary and deadline.
And what should the data types be?
Well the beneficiary will be identified by his
or her public key or rather public key hash or
to be even more precise, payment public key hash.
So that will be the hash of his public payment key.
And the deadline, as we saw before
Plutus uses real time, POSIX time.
So this is the datum.
And we can derive a show instance,
which maybe useful for debugging.
So that we can display values
of this type in the console.
And as I also explained last time, we
don't have to write to data or from data
instances by hand, we can use template
Haskell with this unstable make is data.
Although in production, we would probably
not use the unstable, but the stable version.
But for simplicity, we can just do it like this.
Now the interesting part is the validator function.
And as we know, it takes the datum, the
redeemer, the context and returns a bool if
we use typed Plutus, which we want to do.
So we just talked about the datum type.
We use our custom vesting datum for that.
So what about the redeemer?
So the question is, does the beneficiary
need any additional information when he wants
to redeem the gift, the deposited money.
And in this case, I think we don't
need any additional information.
So all the beneficiary has to do is once the
deadline has been reached, just try to unlock
the UTxO sitting at the vesting script address.
So there is no additional information needed
as long as the beneficiary signs a transaction.
And as long as the deadline has been reached,
the funds should be his and should be possible
for him to use an output sitting at this vesting
address, as an input for his transaction and
then do with it whatever he or she wants.
Which means, so the first argument, the datum must
be of type vesting datum and the second argument,
the redeem we don't need any additional information.
So we can just use the unit type.
And the third argument is of type, script context.
And we can give names.
So we call the datum dat, the redeemer will always
be unit because that's the only value of type unit.
And this time we actually
have to look at the context.
So we can just use an underscore
as we did in our previous examples.
So we give the context a
name as well, we call it ctx.
Okay, and under which conditions should it
be possible to unlock a UTxO sitting at this
address, whether as I said before, the transaction
that unlocks must be signed by the beneficiary
and the deadline must have been reached.
So I'm using this trace if false again,
to, if something goes wrong, to give
some debbug information or tracing
information about the costs of the failure.
So this is the first condition we want
to check that the beneficiary signed.
So we just give this debbug information
in case something went wrong.
This condition was not satisfied,
beneficiary's signature missing.
And then delegate the actual logic to a
helper function signed by a beneficiary.
And additionally we've wanted
the deadline has been reached.
So we will define a second helper
function, deadline reached.
And if it hasn't been reached the given
appropriate message, deadline not reached.
So let's look at these helper
functions, they are refreshingly short.
So first we need this Tx info field of the
script context and we need that more than once.
So I extracted that, so I defined that first here.
So info is just the Tx info
field of the script context.
And now we have to implement these two conditions,
signed by beneficiary, deadline reached.
So signed by beneficiary, there's actually
a helper function called Tx signed by that
takes a Tx info, which we have defined here.
And it takes a public key hash.
And the meaning obviously is that this is
true if and only if the transaction has
been signed by the owner of this public
key hash, that's the second argument.
We do have the required signature, the public key
hash in the form of the beneficiary of the datum.
So we just grab that, so this field.
So now we have this payment pub
key hash of the beneficiary.
Unfortunately, the Tx signed by doesn't expect the
payment pub key hash, but just the pub key hash.
But if we look at the definition
of payment pub key hash.
Then here we see it's simply a
newtype wrapper around a pub key hash.
So there's just for type safety that we don't
confuse different types of pub key hashes,
but the underlying data representation is
actually the same, is just the pub key hash.
Which means that by applying unpayment
pub key hash to our payment pub key hash
we get to the underlying pub key hash.
So this, so we have the datum, the beneficiary gives
us this first field, type payment pub key hash.
Then by applying unpayment pub key hash we
get a pub key hash and that we can pass a
second argument to the Tx signed by function.
That's exactly what we want.
Other more interesting condition is
the second one, deadline reached.
If we look at this crew diagram, so this
is time and let's say the deadline is here.
And let's consider a transaction with...
let's first say this validity interval.
So recall what that means, before
the validator script is run.
Other checks are made including the time check.
So the node checks whether the current time
falls into the valid range of the transaction.
And only then it's the validator run.
So we know now that we in the validator, the current
time lives somewhere in the validity interval.
But if this here, the first one
would be the validity interval.
Then the current time could be, for example, here.
Which would be fine, that would be
after the deadline, but it could also
be here, which would not be fine.
That would be before the deadline.
So this validity interval is not good for us.
We mustn't declare the transaction to be
valid if this is the validity interval.
This on the other hand is fine.
We still don't know where the current time
exactly is, it can be anywhere in this interval.
But no matter where it is after the deadline.
So we must check that we have this situation.
That the whole interval is
to the right of the deadline.
And one way to do is, is to use this contains
function that we played with earlier.
And, look at this interval, the half
open interval that starts at the
deadline and stretches into infinity.
And if this interval contains the validity
interval of the transaction, then we are good.
Then we know no matter where the current
time is, it will be after the deadline.
So we know the deadline is the second field from our
datum which we can get with the deadline accessor.
So this is now the deadline.
And we have the info valid range that we
discussed earlier from the transaction
that we get from the Tx info field.
And as long as the current time interval is
contained in this one, we can be sure that
no matter what the actual current time is,
it will definitely be after the deadline.
And that's what we want.
So this is a way to define
this deadline reach condition.
And we have the signed by beneficiary
and the combination of the two logical
and gives us the logic we want.
So a UTxO sitting at this vesting address
can only be unlocked by a transaction
that has been signed by the beneficiary
and where the deadline has been reached.
As always the validator is the heart
of the Plutus smart contract that
contains the actual business logic.
But in addition to that, as we have learned
last week, it needs some boiler plate.
So as I explained when I talked
about typed Plutus contracts.
We need this dummy type, I in this case
called it vesting where we encode the
types of the datum and the redeemer.
So in our case vesting, datum and unit.
And then just following the same schema that
we introduced last week, we can compile our
Haskell code to an actual Plutus validator,
typed validator like this, following the
same process that we learn last time.
And once we have that, we can get the
untyped validator and the validator hash.
And the address, the actual address corresponding
to this script, to this validator as last week.
And I should also mentioned that at the top of the
module, I added some additional GHC extensions,
like derive any class and drive generic.
And I also added some imports, like
to json, from json, generic and so on.
So let's briefly look at the off-chain part.
So, this type here, vesting schema defines the
endpoints that we want to expose to the user.
And as before in our silly example from
last week, called them give and grab.
So give is for the person that wants to
set up this vesting contract and then
grab for the beneficiary to collect.
So what parameters do we need?
For give, I mean, what this endpoint will do,
is it will create a UTxO at the vesting address
with the specified amount and the correct datum.
And if you recall our vesting datum
contains the beneficiary and the deadline.
So, this give endpoint must in particular
know those, the beneficiary and the deadline.
So this is here.
And we also of course, have to specify how
much money we want to put at this UTxO.
Therefore I need the third field, the amount.
The grab endpoint on the other
hand, doesn't need any parameters.
Because the beneficiary will just look
for UTxOs sitting at the vesting address.
And then can check whether he is the beneficiary.
And whether the deadline has already passed.
And can then pick those UTxOs and consume them.
And we know from the way that we wrote the
validator, that that will then succeed and
no additional information has to be supplied.
Let's briefly look at the endpoints.
First at give.
So it takes the give parameters.
And first I compute the datum I want to use.
So recall I need the beneficiary and
the deadline, and I can get those simply
from reading it from the give parameters.
Now for the transaction, I need as constraint
that I want to create a transaction that
has an output at the script address.
So I use this must pay to the script
with the datum I just defined.
And then I must provide the value.
So I take the value the amount from the
give parameters and then use this function
here to convert that to a value in lovelace.
The rest is as before I just
changed the log message.
So I mentioned the amount, the
beneficiary and the deadline.
Now for the grab, that's a bit more involved.
Because there can be many
UTxOs at this vesting address.
And some of them might not be suitable for me.
Either because I am not the beneficiary or
because the deadline has not yet passed.
So I grabbed the current time.
I look up my own payment pub key hash.
Then I get all the UTxOs
sitting at the script address.
But of course not all of them may be usable for me.
Either because I'm not the beneficiary or
because the deadline has not yet been reached.
So I filter those UTxOs using this is suitable
helper function, which is defined down here.
And its arguments it gets my own payment
pub key hash and the current time.
Then the output that I found, the UTxO.
And how do I do that?
I check the datum of this output and there
are two cases, it can either just be a hash.
This is actually the default case
as I mentioned several times before.
When you create a transaction that has an output
at the script address, you are not required
to include the datum, just the datum hash.
So, there can be output's there that
just contain the hash, not the datum.
But in such a case, I have no way to know whether
I'm the beneficiary and what the deadline is.
Because I'm not able to compute the
actual datum when I just know the hash.
So in that case, that's this left case.
I can't do anything, so I forget about that UTxO.
And if there is an actual datum
attached in the transaction.
Then I try to deserialize that to the
right type, our vesting datum type.
If that fails, I also drop the UTxO.
And if it succeeds, I have to check that I am the
beneficiary and that the deadline lives in the past.
So that now the current time is after the deadline.
So at this point, the UTxOs contain all the
UTxOs where I'm the beneficiary and where
the deadline has already been reached.
And if I'm left with no UTxOs, then I just log
a message that there are no available gifts.
And if there's at least one, then I try to
create a transaction that collects all of
them at the same time in one transaction.
Actually in the real world, depending on the setup
and the situation, there may be too many UTxOs for
me to use them all as inputs to a single transaction
because transactions can only be of limited size.
So to keep it simple, I forget about this case,
so I assume that there won't be that many gifts
lying around for me, waiting for me to be grabbed.
So I just get all the tx orefs, the
references of the UTxOs I want to collect.
And I need to create this look
up that contains the UTxOs.
And also the validator of the script.
And then for the constraints of the transaction I
want to construct here I say that I want to spend
the script output given by this reference where I
basically loop over all the references I found here.
So I loop over all the UTxOs, the
suitable ones, that I want to collect.
And I say that I want to spend each of those.
So I just have to give the reference and then the
redeemer and we are always using the unit redeemer.
Is a very common case, therefore there's a specific
value defined in the Plutus libraries called
unit redeemer that gives me this unit redeemer.
And now this is something new
that we haven't seen before.
I conscious create a default transaction
with the infinite validity interval.
Because now I must make sure that I
specify in the transaction that it's later
than now, later than the current time.
Because otherwise validation will fail
because then the validator won't be able to
be sure that the deadline has already passed.
And then as before I use one of these
variations of subnet transaction, where can
specify the lookups and these constraints.
And I wait for confirmation and then log a message.
And finally, I just bundle up
these two endpoints as before.
So I give the choice between
give and grab and then recourse.
So once a give or grab has happened,
we can do another give or grab.
Let's try this in the playground.
First, let's add an additional wallet.
And the idea is that wallet one makes
gifts to wallet two and wallet three.
And then wallet two and
wallet three try to grab them.
So let's start by finding the
skeleton of what I want to do.
So wallet one starts with a give
and let's wait for one slot.
And then there's another give.
We wait for yet another slot.
Normally it should be possible for wallet
one to make all the gifts in one slot.
So it wouldn't need to wait in between, but
the way I defined the contracts, if you recall.
After doing give or also a grab, I always
wait for confirmation of the transaction.
Maybe I shouldn't have, but I did.
So the endpoint won't be available again
until the transaction has been confirmed.
So the way I've wrote it, we have to
wait in between these give actions.
So let's do the third one.
Now let's say the first two gifts are to wallet two.
But with different deadlines,
let's say, slot 10 and slot 20.
And the last one should be to
wallet three also with deadline...
let's say slot 10.
So, if wallet two and three wait until slot 11.
They should be able to get the
gifts, but not the second one.
The one that's only due in slot 20.
So let's wait until slot 11.
And then both two and three try to grab.
And then let's wait another...
I don't know, five slots just to be sure.
So that's the idea.
So now we encounter the first
problem in order to call give.
We need to get the public key hash or the payment
public key hash of the wallets two and three.
So how do we find out what those are?
If we go to the repl and import wallet emulator.
There's a type wallet defined.
And that wraps a wallet ID and that
some opaque type can't directly handle.
So, actually this wallet type represents
real wallets like a Daedalus wallet.
But also a so-called mock wallets that
are, for example, used in the playground.
So they are both combined under this wallet type.
And, actually you can get to the mock wallets
once in the playground with the function
called known wallet, and it takes an integer.
So for example, known wallet
two, known wallet three.
And there's also a function called mock wallet
payment pub key hash, which takes a wallet.
And if it happens to be a mock wallet,
then it returns the payment pub key hash.
And if it's a real wallet like Daedalus
wallet it would produce an error.
So, we can get the payment pub key hash
of wallets two and three like this.
So that's what we can use.
So let's start with wallet two.
So, let's say the first two
gives I said are to wallet two.
And the third one is to wallet three.
Now, the next problem we have is the deadlines,
but I already showed you in the first lecture
for the auction example, how you can convert
slots to POSIX time in the playground.
So let's find out what slot 10 and 20
are in POSIX time in the playground.
So this is the POSIX time corresponding to slot 10.
And this is the POSIX time corresponding to slot 20.
I want it to use 10 for the
first and the third gift.
And 20 for the second one.
Now amounts, let's say each gift is 30 ADA.
Okay.
Let's go through it again.
The first gift from wallet one to wallet
two with a deadline of slot 10 30 ADA.
Second gift again to wallet two,
but deadline slot 20 30 ADA.
Final gift to wallet three, deadline slot 10 30 ADA.
Then we wait until slot 11.
So that's after the slot 10 deadline,
but before this slot 20 deadline.
And then wallet two and three try to grab.
So let's see what happens.
Okay.
Looking good.
So let's go through the transactions.
Slot zero, that's again, the Genesis
transaction where the three wallets get
their initial funds of 100 ADA each.
Slot one is the first gift.
So wallet one uses input its 100 ADA
has to pay a fee, get some change
and 30 ADA end up in the script.
Second gift.
It's very similar.
Third gift as well.
And now these two, both happened in slot 12.
So this is incidentally the grab of wallet three.
So the input is this one UTxO, the one
gift waiting there for wallet three.
And it ends up belonging to wallet three.
And finally, this should be the
one belonging to wallet two.
Also picks up the gift and gets the 30 ADA.
But the third gift is still sitting
there because we aren't in slot 20 yet.
We can try what happens if we
wait until slot 20 instead.
So, let me change this from 11 to 21 and try again.
So these should all look exactly the same.
This is now wallet three that also looks the same.
Wallet three of course could also
have grabbed at slot 11 already.
But it doesn't matter if it waits until slot 21.
But here now we see that the way we've
wrote the grab endpoint actually works.
So if there's more than one gift available, all
of them are picked up in the same transaction.
So now both gifts for wallet two are
available, because we are now in slot 21.
So both deadlines have passed and
correctly our off-chain code same as a
transaction that uses both of them as input.
And then roughly 60 ADA end up in wallet two.
So everything seems to work as expected.
There's one thing I should point out
that I wrote the off-chain code, the
wallet code, in a way that only submits a
transaction if it can actually grab the UTxO.
For recall, I filter the UTxO to check that I
am the beneficiary and the deadline has passed.
Which means that we don't
really exercise the validator.
Because we only send transactions to the...
to the blockchain that then get
validated that will pass validation.
That's how we wrote the wallet code.
So if you want to actually test the validator,
you would have to modify the wallet code.
If you like, you can do that as an option homework.
So remove these checks in the wallet
and just try to grab everything.
And then it should fail if you
are not the beneficiary or if the
deadline has not yet been reached.
And then it should fail during validation,
not already just in the wallet, not
even submitting the transaction.
So we always have to be
careful to keep that in mind.
Everybody of course can write off-chain code.
So even though now it works.
As long as you use the grab
endpoint that I provided.
I mean, I wrote it in a way that you never
try to claim something that's not for you.
But of course, somebody else could write different
piece of off-chain code that doesn't try that.
And then if your validator is not correct.
If it, for example, forgets to check
the beneficiary or the deadline and
something could go horribly wrong.
So we must keep that in mind that only because
it works for the endpoints you have provided
doesn't mean that somebody else couldn't come
up with other endpoints where it doesn't work.
Okay.
So this is the vesting example, where we made
use of the context for the first time and
where we made use of this valid time interval
in the transaction to implement a deadline.